Guide to the Millar Burrows Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Millar Burrows Papers
1913-1981
RG 71
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, writings, photographs, and slides document Burrows' life and work. Millar Burrows (1889-1980) was Winkley Professor of Biblical Theology at Yale from 1934 to 1958.
Burrows, Millar, 1889-1980
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1889 Born in Wyoming, Ohio
1912 B.A., Cornell University
1915 B.D., Union Theological Seminary, New York
1915-1919 Pastorate in Wallace, Texas
1919-1920 Supervisor, Texas Church Survey
1920-1923 Professor of Biblical History and Literature, Tusculum College, Tenn.
1925 Ph.D., Yale University
1925-1928 Assistant professor, Biblical Literature and History of Religion, Brown University
1928-1932 Associate professor, Brown
1932-1934 Professor, Brown
1934-1948 President, American School for Oriental Research, Jersalem
1934-1958 Winkley Professor of Biblical Theology, Yale Divinity School
1950-1958 Chairman, Department of Near Eastern Languages and Literatures, Yale
1960 D.D., Oberlin
1961 D.D., Yale, Brown
1980 Died
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, notes, writings, photographs, and slides document Burrows' life and work.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1934-1979
II. Notes
III. Sermons, Lectures, Interviews, 1943-1979, n.d.
IV. Writings, 1925-1978, n.d.
V. Slides and Photographs
VI. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1913-1981, n.d.
Educators; Burrows, Millar, 1889-1980; Yale University. Divinity School -- Faculty
- Correspondence, 1934-1979; Series I
  - Related to appointment and promotions at Yale, 1934-1958 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1957-1962, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Related to work on the Revised Standard Version of the Bible, incl. to/from Herbert May and Luther Weigle, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - To/from American School for Oriental Research, incl. minutes, 1965, 1970-1979 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Notes, n.d.; Series II
  - Notebook of Biblical place names, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notebook: "Collation of Isaiah Ms.", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Related to Revised Standard Version of the Bible, ca. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Notecards: related to New Testament parables, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Notecards: miscellaneous research notes (4"x6"), n.d. (Box 3)
  - Notecards: miscellaneous research notes (3"x5"), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - List of miracles and parables in New Testament (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Sermons, lectures, interviews, 1943-1979, n.d; Series III
  - Various, 1943-1979, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11-13)
- Writings, 1925-1978, n.d; Series IV
  - Bibliographies of Burrows' works, 1959, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Book reviews by Burrows, 1937-1972 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Published articles by Burrows, 1925-1957, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 16-23)
  - Writings by others, incl. reviews of Burrows' works, 1949, 1978, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Slides and Photographs, Series V
  - Slides
    - More than 1500 color slides documenting Burrows' travels to Near East and elsewhere, 1938-1960 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Photographs
    - 2 albums documenting trips to Near East and elsewhere (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - 4 albums documenting trips to Near East, and the New Haven area (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Album of family photographs (Box OV2)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1913-1981, n.d.; Series VI
  - Biographical documentation, 1956-1981, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - The Book of Common Worship: Burrows' copy with notes and inserts (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - The Cup and the Unicorn: 92 page commemorative booklet prepared by Burrows' son, Edwin Gladding Burrows, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Tusculum College yearbook, 1921 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Documents related to Burrows' election as Fellow of American Academy of Arts and Sciences, his D.D. from Oberlin, and his D.D. from Yale, 1949, 1960, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Cassette audiotape with commentary by Yigael Yadin on the Shrine of the Book (Box 8, Folder 33, Item barcode 39002125994898)
  - Cornell University plaque (Box OV1)
  - Scrapbook of programmes from theater and musical events attended by Burrows, 1913-1958 (Box OV1)